Before RDA, KRS (cataloging rules were followed for Swedish libraries).
Imported items may be made according to RDA, AACR2 or national cataloging rules.
The main rule is that descriptions in Libris that follow other cataloging rules other than RDA
not to be redone according to RDA.
The RDA is developed by the RSC (RDA Steering Committee) consisting of representatives from different countries.
The goal is for all continents to be represented and it is a work that is ongoing.
RDA was completed in 2010 and then replaced AACR2 on which our previous cataloging rules, KRS, are based on.
The Library of Congress was the first to switch to RDA.
They went over 2013.
KB switched to RDA in 2017.
RDA is gathered in the online service RDA Toolkit.
Swedish, publicly funded libraries have access to RDA Toolkit through a subscription that KB has.
4: Subjects, objects, events, locations
Places are the only chapter in section 4 that contains information.
It was thought that the other chapters would be added after the release of RDA Toolkit, but it never happened.
Now that you have launched the beta version of the new RDA Toolkit, there is only space left of the entities in section 4.
Section 5-10 gives you guidelines on how to describe relationships between the entities.
A number of appendix that contains rules for upper and lower case, for example,
Abbreviations and symbols are also available.
There are also appendix with different types of relationship designations to indicate more
specific relationships between the units.
Appendix I-M (Relationships)
Relationships between a resource and agents linked to the resource.
It is available in appendix I.
The four description methods are: unstructured description, structured description,
Identifier and uri.
Unstructured description
Yes, there may be remarks, quotes from different sources and information transferred from the manifestation.
"Mechanical" transfer, ie
That you write what stands.
They are manipulated according to certain rules that apply to punctuation, upper and lower case, etc.
And unstructured description cannot be understood by machines.
Structured description
We have an example under publishing details:
"Take what you see" applies to each individual element, ie.
Follow the formulation of the resource, but
Enter the elements in a particular order.
They indicated which elements must be stated at each level of description.
In Libris, the description levels remain.
In RDA there are really no description levels.
Instead, talking about nuclear elements
Or core elements as it is called in English.
The picture shows the element title (manifestation) in RDA Toolkit.
Title has several sub -elements.
The main title is a nuclear element.
All other titles are optional, e.g.
Other title information, variant titles.
Nuclear elements - what does RDA say?
Well, a description of an entity should contain all nuclear elements that are applicable and easily accessible.
It should also contain all other elements necessary to distinguish
the entity from other similar entities.
Think about the user's needs and use the catalog's judgment.